<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>KinOath, web version</title>
  <subtitle>Manual</subtitle>
  <bookinfo>
    <releaseinfo>April 2012</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo>The latest version can be downloaded from <ulink
        url="www.lat-mpi.eu/tools/browser/">www.lat-mpi.eu/tools/browser/</ulink></releaseinfo>
    <author>
      <surname>F.Bechis (<ulink url="mailto:Francesca.Bechis@mpi.nl"
        >Francesca.Bechis@mpi.nl</ulink>)</surname>
    </author>
  </bookinfo>
  <preface id="Pre_Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      <informaltable id="portal-columns">
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">KinOath is a kinship application with the primary goal of
              connecting kinship data with archived data, such as audio, video or written resources
              while also being closely integrated with the archive software such as Arbil. Beyond
              this primary goal it is designed to be flexible and culturally nonspecific, such that
              culturally different social structures can equally be represented. Kin type strings
              are used throughout the application for constructing and searching data sets. The
              representation of kin terms is also integrated into the application allowing
              comparative diagrams of kin terms. Graphical representation of the data is an
              important part of the application and the diagrams produced are intended to very
              flexible and of publishable quality.</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </informaltable>
    </para>
  </preface>
  <chapter id="Ch_Navigating_the_IMDI_Browser_web_version">
    <title>Navigating KinOath</title>
    <para>KinOath is part of the Language Archiving Technology suite. You will find a link to the
      program on the LAT web page <ulink url="http://www.lat-mpi.eu/tools/browser/"
        >http://www.lat-mpi.eu/tools/kinoath/</ulink> . KinOath is an online tool, it does not need
      to be installed, but you will need Java installed on your machine for it to run. For more
      information on Java and how to install it <ulink url="http://java.com/en/"
        >http://java.com/en/</ulink>. </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Menus</title>
    <para>Once KinOath has been opened, the various diagrams and their relative options can be
      accessed through a number of menus collocated at the top of the page. </para>
    <section>
      <title>File menu</title>
      <para>The first one is the <emphasis role="bold">File</emphasis> menu, which includes the
        following options:</para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">New (default diagram)</emphasis>: this option allows you to
              open a new diagram. It says 'default' because the type of diagram which is opened is
              the same as the one which was previously set as default diagram (see option 'Set
              Default Diagram as' below). </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">New Diagram of Type</emphasis>: this option allows you to
              open a new diagram choosing among the different types given (see section
              2.1.1.)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Open</emphasis>: this option allows you to open a new
              diagram file from a directory in your computer. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Open Recent Diagram</emphasis>: through this option you can
              select and re-open one of the diagrams which were previously opened. If you want to
              delete the list you can select <emphasis role="bold">Clear list</emphasis>  (at the
              end of the list). </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Open Sample Diagram</emphasis>: KinOath includes a number of
              sample diagrams through which you can observe how the program works. You can see them
              by selecting this option. (See section 2.1.2.)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Import Gedcom / CSV File</emphasis>: this option allows you
              to import in KinOath files in either Gedcom or CSV format. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Import Sample Data</emphasis>: the <emphasis role="bold"
                >Query Diagram</emphasis> requires data to be imported. A list of sample data is
              accessible via this option.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Entity Upload</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">this
                option is not available at the moment. It will be functioning for the next release
                of KinOath</emphasis>. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Save as</emphasis>: when selecting this option you will be
              asked to choose a directory and enter a file name in order to save the file. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Export as PDF</emphasis>: this option allows you to export
              the file to a directory in PDF format.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Export to R / SPSS</emphasis>: this option allows you to
              export a KinOath diagram to either R or SPSS, two programs for statistical computing.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Close</emphasis>: clicking on this option will close the
              program.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Set Default Diagram as</emphasis>: through this option you
              can choose a particular type of diagram and set it as the default diagram, so that
              when you open KinOath again, this will show you the specific diagram type you
              chose.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Exit</emphasis>:  as with 'Close', clicking on this option
              will close the program.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <section>
        <title>Diagram Types</title>
        <para>Through the option 'New Diagram of Type' a number of different diagrams can be opened: </para>
        <para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Standard Diagram (database driven)</emphasis>: when
                selecting this type, a new page of KinOath will open, with a main, blank panel and a
                smaller panel on the left called <emphasis role="bold">Diagram Tree</emphasis>. You
                can create a new diagram from scratch using the several options of the menu that
                comes out when right clicking in the main panel:<orderedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Add</emphasis>: you may decide to add an <emphasis
                        role="bold">Individual</emphasis> or a <emphasis role="bold"
                        >Chromosome_Example</emphasis> to your diagram. In both cases, a new entity
                      will appear under the form of a small square, representing an unspecified ego.
                      If you select that entity you will see, at the bottom of the page, a table
                      with information to fill in: 'Name', 'Date of Birth', 'Date of Death',
                      'Gender' (in the case of the chromosome example you will also see the voice
                      'Chromosome'). Once the data regarding an ego have been entered you can save
                      them either by clicking on the ego itself, or by choosing - from the right
                      click menu - the option <emphasis role="bold">Save All Data
                      Changes</emphasis>.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Add Geometry</emphasis>: its sub-options are:
                        <emphasis role="bold">Add Label</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Add
                        Circle</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Add Square</emphasis>, <emphasis
                        role="bold"><emphasis role="italic"><emphasis role="underline">Add
                            Polyline</emphasis></emphasis></emphasis>, and <emphasis role="bold">Add
                        Ellipse</emphasis>. The first (label) allows you to enter a label for your
                      diagram, and you can do it by entering the text into a small window opening at
                      the bottom of the page when the option is selected. The other four are graphic
                      options you can use to create different kin groups (circle, square, ellipse)
                      or to link the entities with more than one single line (polyline).</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Delete</emphasis>: this option allows you to delete
                      the entity/ies you created from the diagram but also from the database.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Merge Selected Entities</emphasis>: you can use this
                      option when, for example, you have two separate entities including different
                      data but you discover that they are the same individual, and therefore you
                      want to make them merge into a single one. </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Duplicate Selected Entities</emphasis>: when
                      choosing this option, the entity/ies previously selected will be doubled.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Add Relations</emphasis>: once several, single
                      entities have been created you may want to create relations between them. To
                      this purpose, select how many entities you need (by clicking on them while
                      holding down the SHIFT button on the keyboard) and right click. You can choose
                      between: <emphasis role="bold">sibling</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold"
                        >ancestor</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">descendant</emphasis>, <emphasis
                        role="bold">union</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">kinterm</emphasis>,
                        <emphasis role="bold">other</emphasis>. In addition, if you want to add only
                      a 'descendant' or 'ancestor' relation, you can simply select one entity and
                      drag the blue line to the other. </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Remove Relations</emphasis>: you may also want to
                      change some of the relations created. To do so, select the necessary entities,
                      right click, and choose 'Remove Relations' - <emphasis role="bold">Remove
                        relations between selected</emphasis>.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Set as ego (replacing list)</emphasis>: in the
                      diagram tree panel on the left you see three lists, <emphasis role="bold"
                        >Ego</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Required</emphasis>, and <emphasis
                        role="bold">Implied</emphasis>. When you create new entities they
                      automatically go under the 'Required' list or, depending on the relations that
                      have been created, under the 'Implied' list. However, if you want to create an
                      egocentric diagram you can select one of the entities and - through 'Set as
                      ego' - transfer it to the 'Ego' list. This will highlighted in black. You can
                      also create socialcentric diagrams, in which no particular ego is highlighted.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Add to ego list</emphasis>: this option is similar
                      to the previous one. You can select entities and add them to the 'Ego' list on
                      the left.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Remove from ego list</emphasis>: through this option
                      you can move entities from the 'Ego' list back to the 'Required' list. </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Keep on diagram</emphasis>: with this option you
                      decide to keep the selected entity/ies onto the digram.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Release from the diagram</emphasis>: with this
                      option you remove the selected entity/ies from the diagram, but in this case
                      it/they remain(s) in the database, unlike with the option 'Delete'.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Reset Zoom</emphasis>: when selecting this option
                      the layout of the diagram returns back to its default size.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Reset Layout</emphasis>: it can happen, when you
                      select many entities at a time (see 'Archive Data Linker' diagram below) that
                      they overlap in the diagram so you cannot see them clearly. By resetting the
                      layout such entities are distanced from each other. </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Search Entity Service</emphasis>:  <emphasis
                        role="italic"><emphasis role="underline">chiedi a Peter di
                          rispiegartelo</emphasis></emphasis></para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Save All Data Changes</emphasis>: see point 1.
                      above. </para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Freeform diagram (transient)</emphasis>: when selecting
                this type, a new page of KinOath will open, with a main, blank panel and a smaller
                panel on the top called <emphasis role="bold">Kin Type Strings</emphasis>. Also here
                you can create diagrams from scratch but the difference with the previous case is
                that you need to enter strings in the panel on the top of the page, using precise
                kin types definitions. Hereinafter there is a list of the principal ones (which can
                be found also via 'Panels' > 'Diagram Settings' > 'Kin Type Definitions'):</para>
              <para>E = ego; Ef = ego female; Em = ego male; x = undefied</para>
              <para>F or Fa = father; M or Mo = mother; P or Pa = parent</para>
              <para>B or Br = brother; Z or Si = sister; Sb = sibling</para>
              <para>S or So = son; D or Da = daughter; C or Ch = child</para>
              <para>H or Hu = husband; W or Wi = wife; Sp = spouse</para>
              <para>* = any relation</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Kin Terms Diagram</emphasis>: this type of diagram is
                useful when you want to observe how social relations are named within a given
                language and culture (see figure below). When you choose this diagram a new page of
                KinOath opens, with a main, blank panel, and a smaller panel on the right called
                  <emphasis role="bold">Kin Term Group</emphasis>. In the latter, you can see a
                table that you have to fill in to create your diagram: in the first space (<emphasis
                  role="bold">Kin Term</emphasis>) you have to enter the kin terms that represent
                also the labels of the diagram; in the second (<emphasis role="bold">Referent Kin
                  Type Strings</emphasis>) you have to enter, for each kin term, its corresponding
                definition following the ones listed in the Freeform Diagram; in the fourth
                  (<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>) you can add, for example, an
                English gloss if the kin terms entered are in another language. In addition, you can
                decide to: a) show the kin terms on the diagram, or to hide them, by checking or
                unckecking the option <emphasis role="bold">Show on graph</emphasis>, above the
                table; b) delete some of the kin terms entered in the table by checking them and
                then clicking on <emphasis role="bold">Delete Selected</emphasis>, or delete the
                entire group by simply clicking on <emphasis role="bold">Delete Group</emphasis>. </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Query Diagram</emphasis>: When you choose this diagram a
                new page of KinOath opens, with a main, blank panel, the <emphasis role="bold"
                  >Diagram Tree</emphasis> panel on the left, and the <emphasis role="bold">Kin Type
                  Strings</emphasis> panel on the top. This type allows you to search for entities
                within an already constructed diagram. A list of sample data is accessible through
                File menu > Import Sample Data. Once you have imported such data you can make a
                query using basically the definitions listed in the Freeform Diagram, plus other
                constraints such as names, dates, etc. (see figure below). The entities you have
                searched for appear both in the tree on the left and in the main panel. </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Entity Search</emphasis>: this diagram functions in, more
                or less, the same way as the query diagram. When you choose it a new page of KinOath
                opens, with a main, blank panel, the <emphasis role="bold">Diagram Tree</emphasis>
                panel on the left, and another small panel on the right called <emphasis role="bold"
                  >Search Entities</emphasis>. Here again the search is made on an already existent
                diagram, and therefore you need to import some data first. Once the data have been
                imported you make your search by entering a name in the <emphasis role="bold"
                  >Search</emphasis> space of the right panel. The latter contains an option called
                  <emphasis role="bold">Expand selection by kin type string</emphasis>. If you check
                it and you enter a kin definition, the corresponding entities will appear on the
                diagram and in the diagram tree in the implied list. </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Archive Data Linker</emphasis>: When you choose this
                diagram a new page of KinOath opens, with a main, blank panel, the <emphasis
                  role="bold">Diagram Tree</emphasis> panel on the left, and another panel on the
                right called <emphasis role="bold">Archive Linker</emphasis>. The latter contains
                the IMDI corpora tree. From a session node of the tree you can take a group of, or
                the single, actors, and drag them to the main panel. Under each of them you will see
                the reference to the archive and, at the bottom of the page, a table containing
                information about them and the corresponding session node of the IMDI tree. You can
                then link the selected entities by creating relations and/or add, for example, media
                files, by taking and drag them to the diagram tree on the left under the entity you
                want them to belong to. </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Sample Diagrams</title>
        <para>Apart from the possibility to work on new diagrams, KinOath includes also a list of
          sample diagrams which you can observe to get to know the program and its functionalities,
          and which you can reach through the option 'Open Sample Diagram' from the File menu. These
          are: Freeform Diagram Syntax, Query Diagram Syntax, Hawaiian Kin Terms, Japanese Kin
          Terms, Swedish Kin Terms, Named Transient Entities, Matrimonial Ring Examples, Charles II
          of Spain, and Imported Data Query Example (ANTONIO DE PAULA PESSOA DE /FIGUEIREDO/).
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Edit menu</title>
      <para>This menu contains some options linked to the modification of a diagram: </para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Select All</emphasis>: by clicking on this option all the
              entities belonging to the all the diagrams present in the main panel will be
              highlighted.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Select Related</emphasis>:  if you select one entity and
              then choose this option, all the entities related to the one selected will be
              hightlighted.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Expand Selection</emphasis>: if you select one entity and
              then choose this option, only the entities immediately related to the one selected
              will be highlighted. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Deselect All</emphasis>: this option is for deselecting the
              entities previously selected. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recalculate the Diagram</emphasis>: this option allows you
              to partially modify, or totally recreate, the diagram. Once selected you are allowed
              to add entities (in the standard diagram), constraints to these (freeform, query, and
              entity search diagrams), or kin terms and kin groups (kin terms diagram).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Diagram Options menu</title>
      <para>This menu contains options regarding the layout of the diagram which only have to
        checked or unchecked acoording to the needs. </para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Snap To Grid</emphasis>: if checked, this option allows you
              to move the entity in all directions. If not, you can move the entity just on the
              sides (see figure below).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Highlight Selected Relations</emphasis>: if checked, when
              you select one entity, the relations that this has with other,  immediately close
              entities will be highlighted in blue. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Show Diagram Border</emphasis>: if checked, you can see the
              border of the diagram (a grey line).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Show Sanguin Lines</emphasis>: if unchecked, the lines
              connecting one entity to the other disappear.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Show Labels</emphasis>: if unchecked, the labels added to
              the individuals (names for example) when creating the diagram disappear. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Show Kin Type Labels</emphasis>: if unchecked, the kin type
              definitions next to the to the labels disappear.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Show Id Labels</emphasis>: an Id is added when the same kin
              type definition is used for different entities, in order to be able to distinguish
              them; it is represented by a #-sign followed by a number. So for example if you have
              two male egos, one will be simply Em, and the other Em - #1. If this option is
              unchecked, you are not able to see Ids.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Show Date Labels</emphasis>: when you create individuals you
              can also enter a date of birth and of death but, unlike with name and gender, you can
              decide whether or not to show such dates; if you want them hidden you have to leave
              this option unchecked.  </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Show Archive Links</emphasis>: this option is valid only for
              the diagram type 'Archive Data Linker' where, when you drag entities from the archive
              into a diagram, you can see also a label of the type: 'archive ref.: 1'. Such label
              disappears if the option 'Show Archive Links' is unchecked. </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Kin Terms menu</title>
      <para>The whole menu is available only for the Kin Terms Diagram, whereas in the other cases
        only the option <emphasis role="bold">New Kin Term Group</emphasis> can be accessed. This
        menu includes the following options:</para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Show</emphasis>: this option allows you to see the kin terms
              panel on the right. If you uncheck it, the panel disappears and all the other menu
              options (see below) are not available anymore. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">New Kin Term Group</emphasis>: this is the only option from
              this menu to be available for all the digram types. By selecting it, a new tab will
              open in the panel on the right in order to add a new group of kin terms. You can
              choose another colour for this new group by clicking on the bar next to <emphasis
                role="bold">Graph Colour</emphasis> (see figure below). The new kin terms will
              appear in the diagram next to the previous ones. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Import</emphasis>: instead of creating a new kin terms group
              from scratch you may decide to import one already existent from a file directory in
              your computer. To do so, click on the 'Import' option and choose the file you want to
              import. The kin terms imported will be added to the ones in the table in the right
              panel and in the diagram also.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Export</emphasis>: with this option you can save (export)
              the kin terms group created to a directory outside KinOath. By selecting this option a
              window will open asking you to choose a directory where to place the file, and a file
              name. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Delete</emphasis>: ???</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Archive Linker menu</title>
      <para><emphasis role="italic">This menu is not fully functional at the moment, but it will be
          from the next version of KinOath, by which time a better and more detailed explanation
          will be included in this manual</emphasis>. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Panels menu</title>
      <para>This menu contains a list of all the panels that can be opened while working on a
        diagram (some of them have already been mentioned when describing the diagram types). You
        can choose which ones you want to open simply by checking them.  </para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Archive Linker</emphasis>: by choosing this option a panel
              will open on the right of the page displaying the IMDI corpora as in the 'Archive Data
              Linker' diagram. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Diagram Settings</emphasis>: by choosing this option a panel
              will open on the top of the page with six tabs:</para>
            <para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Entity Profiles</emphasis>: this tab includes a list
                    of profiles which can be added or removed when creating a diagram ('Individual'
                    and 'Chromosome_Example' seen in section 2.1.1. in the standard diagram are two
                    examples of profiles). They just need to be checked and unchecked.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Kin Type Definitions</emphasis>: this tab includes a
                    list of the main kin type strings with their corresponding definitions (which
                    have also been reported in this manual in section 2.1.1., freeform diagram). You
                    can delete elements of the list by checking them and then clicking on <emphasis
                      role="bold">Delete Delected </emphasis>on the right.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Kin Type Strings</emphasis>: this is the panel the
                    opens up when creating a freeform diagram (see section 2.1.1.), in which you
                    have to enter some strings in order to create individuals, hence
                    diagrams.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Label Fields</emphasis>: this tab contains some
                    information about the entities created by the user (we are referring to the
                    standard diagram type), i.e. name, date of birth, etc. You can delete such
                    pieces of information by clicking on the small squares on the right of the tab.
                    However, they still remain in the table at the bottom of the page (the one
                    filled in when cretaing individuals, so if you want to add them back to the
                    panel on the top you just need to select them (one at a time) and drag them. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Relation Type Definitions</emphasis>: when selecting
                    this tab a sub-table opens. The options of this sub-table displayed here are not
                    mandatory, but if used they may prove useful to simplify the diagram layout.
                    These options are: </para>
                  <para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                      <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Display Name</emphasis>: in this column you can
                          enter the name that you want to give to a particular relation.</para>
                      </listitem>
                      <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Category</emphasis>: in this column you can
                          enter an URL which redirects you to a page containing some additional
                          information about the relation types.</para>
                      </listitem>
                      <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Relation Type</emphasis>: as the name says, in
                          this column you can select a type of relation (sibling, union, etc.),
                          choosing among the various possibilities present in the drop down menu. If
                          you do not want to do it manually, you can select <emphasis role="bold"
                            >Scan For Types</emphasis> under the color table on the right. It will
                          automatically find all the relation types of your diagram and enter them
                          directly in the column Relation Type. </para>
                      </listitem>
                      <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Line Colour</emphasis>: you can choose a
                          different color (from the table on the right) for each of the relation
                          types present in your diagram.</para>
                      </listitem>
                      <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Line Width</emphasis>: ???</para>
                      </listitem>
                      <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Line/Dash</emphasis>: ???</para>
                      </listitem>
                      <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Line Orientation</emphasis>: </para>
                      </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Symbol Fields</emphasis>: according to the features
                    that are attributed to the entities, these get different shapes, for example a
                    female ego is a circle, whereas a male ego is a triangle. Such shapes, however,
                    can be modified by choosing among the possibilities included in the drop down
                    lists on the right of the panel. For instance, you may want circles for male
                    egos and triangles for female egos. </para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Diagram Tree</emphasis>: this panel opens up on the left of
              the page. It displays three possible lists: <emphasis role="bold">Ego</emphasis>,
                <emphasis role="bold">Required</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Implied</emphasis>.
              Let's take the standard diagram type as an example: when you create new individuals,
              they automatically go under the Required list. If you want an egocentric diagram you
              have to add an ego, or several egos, depending on how many diagrams you want to
              create, to the Ego list. The ego/s added to the list go black and represent the
              reference point of your diagram (see figure below). In addition, <emphasis
                role="italic"><emphasis role="underline">..... manca
              implied</emphasis></emphasis></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Export Data</emphasis>: ???</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Kin Terms</emphasis>: this panel opens up automatically when
              working on a Kin Terms Diagram (see section 2.4), since it contains the table with kin
              terms, kin type strings, descriptions, etc.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Kin Type Strings</emphasis>: this panel opens up
              automatically in case of a freeform or a query diagram. In it you type the strings
              necessary to create new individuals (freeform diagram) or to look for them (query
              diagram). </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Search Entities</emphasis>: with this option you can look
              for determined individuals into an already existent diagram which you have to import
              first. </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Window menu</title>
      <para>The options of this menu vary according to how many windows of KinOath have been opened.
        Indeed, it simply consists of a list of the options that have been selected and opened:
        sample diagrams, new diagrams, etc. Each window has its corresponding menu option checked
        (see figure below). </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Help menu</title>
      <para>This menu includes some additional information about the program:</para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">About</emphasis>:</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Help</emphasis>:</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">KinOath Forum (Website)</emphasis>: selecting this option
              will redirect you to this page: http://www.lat-mpi.eu/tools/kinoath/kinoath-forum/, a
              discussion board where you can start discussions about topics relevant to KinOath.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">View Error Log</emphasis>: selecting this option will open a
              page in NotePad.......</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>