<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>KinOath, web version</title>
  <subtitle>Manual</subtitle>
  <bookinfo>
    <releaseinfo>April 2012</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo>The latest version can be downloaded from <ulink
        url="www.lat-mpi.eu/tools/browser/">www.lat-mpi.eu/tools/browser/</ulink></releaseinfo>
    <author>
      <surname>N. Wood (<ulink url="mailto:nick.wood@mpi.nl">nick.wood@mpi.nl</ulink>) and F.Bechis
          (<ulink url="mailto:Francesca.Bechis@mpi.nl">Francesca.Bechis@mpi.nl</ulink>)</surname>
    </author>
  </bookinfo>
  <preface id="Pre_Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      <informaltable id="portal-columns">
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">KinOath is a kinship application with the primary goal of
              connecting kinship data with archived data, such as audio, video or written resources
              while also being closely integrated with the archive software such as Arbil. Beyond
              this primary goal it is designed to be flexible and culturally nonspecific, such that
              culturally different social structures can equally be represented. Kin type strings
              are used throughout the application for constructing and searching data sets. The
              representation of kin terms is also integrated into the application allowing
              comparative diagrams of kin terms. Graphical representation of the data is an
              important part of the application and the diagrams produced are intended to very
              flexible and of publishable quality.</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </informaltable>
    </para>
  </preface>
  <chapter id="Ch_Navigating_the_IMDI_Browser_web_version">
    <title>Navigating KinOath</title>
    <para>KinOath is part of the Language Archiving Technology suite. You will find a link to the
      program on the LAT web page <ulink url="http://www.lat-mpi.eu/tools/browser/"
        >http://www.lat-mpi.eu/tools/kinoath/</ulink> . <figure
        id="Fig_LAT_page_Link_to_IMDI_web_Browser_A">
        <title>LAT page: Link to KinOath (A)</title>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo/>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/latFrontPage.png" scalefit="1"
                width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure></para>
    <para>Since KinOath is an online tool, it does not need to be installed, but you will need Java
      installed on your machine for it to run. For more information on Java and how to install it
        <ulink url="http://java.com/en/">http://java.com/en/</ulink>.</para>
    <para/>
    <section>
      <title/>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>