<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>KinOath Kinship Archiver</title>
  <subtitle>Manual</subtitle>
  <bookinfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/KinOath-512.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <orgname>The Language Archive, MPI for Psycholinguistics, Nijmegen, The Netherlands</orgname>
    
      <releaseinfo>The latest version can be downloaded from <ulink url="http://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/kinoath"
        >http://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/kinoath</ulink></releaseinfo>
      <releaseinfo>This manual was last updated in June 2013</releaseinfo>
      <releaseinfo>Francesca Bechis</releaseinfo>
      
  </bookinfo>
  <preface id="Pre_Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      <informaltable id="portal-columns">
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">KinOath Kinship Archiver is a professional scientific
              general kinship tool, and also and archive retrieval application. It is designed,
              first of all, to link kinship data with archived data such as, for example, media
              resources (i.e. audio files, video files, etc.). Secondly, being culturally
              nonspecific, this program makes it possible for users to create diagrams based on
              culturally, and therefore linguistically, different social structures. Such diagrams
              can then be compared and contrasted. A series of options are included which aim to
              optimize graphical representation of the data, a key feature within KinOath
              environment. </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </informaltable>
    </para>
  </preface>
  <chapter id="Ch_Navigating_the_IMDI_Browser_web_version">
    <title>Navigating KinOath</title>
    <para>KinOath Kinship Archiver is part of the Language Archiving Technology suite. You will find
      a link to the program on the TLA web page <ulink
        url="http://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/kinoath"
        >http://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/kinoath</ulink>. You can either start it - with no
      installation needed - through the option <emphasis role="bold">Run via webstart</emphasis>, or
      you can install it on your computer by selecting one of the installers provided next to
        <emphasis role="bold">Run via webstart</emphasis>. Installers are available for Windows,
      MacOS and Debian. In both cases (webstart and installation), however, you will need Java
      installed on your machine for the application to run. For more information on Java and how to
      install it go to <ulink url="http://java.com/en/">http://java.com/en/</ulink>.</para>
    <para>
      <figure>
        <title>Navigating KinOath</title>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo/>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/StartingKinoath.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Menus</title>
    <para>Once KinOath Kinship Archiver has been opened, the several diagrams and the options
      available for each of them can be accessed through a number of menus located on the top of the
      page. </para>
    <para>
      <figure>
        <title>KinOath menus</title>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo/>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/Menus.png" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>File menu</title>
      <figure>
        <title>File menu</title>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo/>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentwidth="100%" fileref="images/FileMenu2.png" scalefit="1"
                width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>The first menu available is the <emphasis role="bold">File</emphasis> menu (see figure
        above), which includes the following options:</para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">New (default diagram)</emphasis>: this option allows you to
              open a new diagram. It says <emphasis role="italic">default</emphasis> diagram because
              when KinOath opens, it shows the diagram that was previously set as default through
              the option <emphasis role="bold">Set Default Diagram as</emphasis> (see below). </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">New Diagram of Type</emphasis>: this option allows you to
              open a new diagram, choosing among the different types provided (i.e. Standard Diagram
              (database driven); Freeform Diagram (transient); Kin Terms Diagram; Query Diagram;
              Archive Data Linker. See section 2.1.1 below for more detailed information). </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Open Diagram</emphasis>: this option allows you to open a
              diagram choosing from the ones present in your computer directories. Once you have
              selected the file you need, and clicked <emphasis role="bold">Open</emphasis>, the
              file will open in a new page of KinOath. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Open Recent Diagram</emphasis>: through this option you can
              select and re-open one of the diagrams which were previously opened. If you want to
              delete the list of diagrams opened you can select <emphasis role="bold">Clear
                list</emphasis>. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Open Sample Diagram</emphasis>: KinOath includes a number of
              sample diagrams (see section 2.1.2) through which you can observe how the application
              works. You can open and examine these sample diagrams by selecting this option. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Import Gedcom / CSV / TIP File</emphasis>: this option
              allows you to import kinship files in either Gedcom, CSV, or TIP format. Once it is
              selected, a window will open asking you to choose the file to import from a directory.
              The file selected will then open in a new page of KinOath.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Import Sample Data</emphasis>: some of the diagrams require
              data to be imported before starting to work on them. A list of sample data is
              accessible via this option. Once the import is complete a new panel will appear on the
              right of the page containing all the entities imported (<emphasis role="bold">Imported
                Entities</emphasis>). </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Save as</emphasis>: when selecting this option you will be
              asked to choose a directory and enter a file name in order to save the file. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Export as PDF/JPEG/PNG/TIFF</emphasis>: this option allows
              you to export files (in one of the following formats: PDF, JPEG, PNG and TIFF) to a
              directory in your computer. As in the previous option, <emphasis role="bold">Save
                as</emphasis>, when selecting <emphasis role="bold">Export as</emphasis> ... you
              will be asked to choose a directory and a file name plus, in this case, a file format. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Export for R / SPSS</emphasis>: this option allows you to
              export a KinOath diagram to either R or SPSS, two programs you can mainly use to
              statistically analyse your data. The file format is, by deafult, <emphasis
                role="italic">.tab</emphasis>. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Close</emphasis>: clicking on this option will close the
              application.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Set Default Diagram as</emphasis>: through this option you
              can take a certain type of diagram and some diagram settings, and set them as default,
              so that when you start the application again, this will open showing the specific
              diagram and settings you preconfigured. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Exit</emphasis>: as with <emphasis role="bold"
                >Close</emphasis>, clicking on this option will close the application.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <section>
        <title>Diagram Types</title>
        <para>Through the option <emphasis role="bold">New Diagram of Type</emphasis> a number of
          different diagrams can be opened. All the diagrams produced are in a scalable vector
          format of publishing quality and all diagrams can be exported into PDF format. The working
          files are in SVG (Scalable Vector Graphics) format that can be opened in graphics
          applications or viewed in modern web browsers. </para>
        <para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Standard Diagram (database driven)</emphasis>: when
                selecting this type, a new page of KinOath Kinship Archiver will open, with a
                central, blank panel and a smaller panel on the left which includes three tabs:
                  <emphasis role="bold">Search Entities</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Project
                  Tree</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Diagram Tree</emphasis>. Through the
                first one you can search for entities which are already present in the database. </para>
              <para>
                <note>
                  <para>Entities can also be searched with fuzzy matching, and the results can also
                    be expanded through kin type strings entered in the white field located in the
                      <emphasis role="bold">Search Entities</emphasis> tab. As you select different
                    entities, the diagram updates itself accordingly. See the figure below.</para>
                </note>
              </para>
              <para>
                <figure>
                  <title>Search Entities tab</title>
                  <screenshot>
                    <screeninfo/>
                    <mediaobject>
                      <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/FuzzyMatching2.png" contentdepth="100%"
                          scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
                      </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                  </screenshot>
                </figure>
              </para>
              <para>A complete list of such entities is provided in the second tab (<emphasis
                  role="bold">Project Tree</emphasis>). In the third tab (<emphasis role="bold"
                  >Diagram Tree</emphasis>), by contrast, you are able to see the specific entities
                you have selected from the database and/or the ones you have created. As far as new
                entities are concerned, you can create a completely new diagram from scratch using
                the several options of the menu that comes out when right clicking in the main panel:<orderedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Add</emphasis>: you may decide to add to your
                      diagram an <emphasis role="bold">Individual</emphasis>, a <emphasis
                        role="bold">Chromosome_Example</emphasis>, a <emphasis role="bold"
                        >Clan_Example</emphasis>, a <emphasis role="bold">KinTerm</emphasis>, a
                        <emphasis role="bold">Social_Event</emphasis>, or any other entity type
                      selected in the profiles settings (Panels > Diagram Settings > Entity
                      Profiles). In both cases, a new entity will appear, represented by a small
                      square icon (unless configured otherwise). If you select that entity you will
                      see, at the bottom of the page, a table with information to fill in, such as
                      names, dates, genders, etc. Right clicking the table will open a menu with a
                      list of all the possible fields you can add (in alphabetical order);
                      alternatively, you can add a new field yourself, buy selecting the item
                        <emphasis role="bold">Add custom field</emphasis> from the right click menu,
                      and typing the required string, or delete one of the fields by selecting
                      firstly the custom field you want to delete and then the item <emphasis
                        role="bold">Delete ...</emphasis> from the right click menu. Once the data
                      regarding an entity has been entered you can save it either by clicking on the
                      entity itself, or by choosing - from the right click menu - the option
                        <emphasis role="bold">Save All Data Changes</emphasis>.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Add Geometry</emphasis>: its sub-options are:
                        <emphasis role="bold">Add Label</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Add
                        Circle</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Add Square</emphasis>, and
                        <emphasis role="bold">Add Ellipse</emphasis>. The first one (<emphasis
                        role="bold">Add Label</emphasis>) allows you to enter a label for your
                      diagram, and you can do it by entering the text into a small window opening at
                      the bottom of the page when the option is selected. The other three (<emphasis
                        role="bold">Add Circle</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Add
                        Square</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Add Ellipse</emphasis>) are graphic
                      options you can use to differentiate kin groups.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Delete</emphasis>: this option allows you to delete
                      the selected entity from the database and from all diagrams. </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Merge Selected Entities</emphasis>: you can use this
                      option when, for example, you have two separate entities carrying different
                      pieces of information but you find them to be the same individual, and
                      therefore you want to make them merge into a single entity. What results from
                      the merger is a single individual carrying the information of the two merged
                      entities. [Note: at the moment it only merges the entities but not the kinship
                      data that such entities carry]</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Duplicate Selected Entities</emphasis>: when
                      choosing this option, the entity/ies previously selected will be doubled.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Add Relations</emphasis>: once that several, single
                      entities have been created, you may also want to create relations between
                      them. To this purpose, select how many entities you need (by clicking on them
                      while holding down the SHIFT key on the keyboard) and right click. You can
                      choose between: <emphasis role="bold">sibling</emphasis>, <emphasis
                        role="bold">ancestor</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold"
                      >descendant</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">union</emphasis>, <emphasis
                        role="bold">kinterm</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">other</emphasis> (the
                      last one means that the relation connecting two, or more, entities, is not a
                      sanguine relation). In addition, if you want to add only a relation of the
                      type "descendant" or "ancestor", you can simply select one entity and drag the
                      blue line to the other. [Note: as for these two last options, the choice of
                      one or the other depends on which entity you select first. In other words: if
                      you select the parent first, then you have to use the descendant relation,
                      whereas if you select the child first, you will have to choose the ancestor
                      relation.]</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Remove Relations</emphasis>: you may also want to
                      change some of the relations created. To do so, select the necessary entities,
                      right click, and choose "Remove Relations" > <emphasis role="bold">Remove
                        relations between selected</emphasis>.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Set as ego (list will be cleared)</emphasis>: in the
                      "Diagram Tree" panel on the left of the page you see three lists: <emphasis
                        role="bold">Ego</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Required</emphasis>, and
                        <emphasis role="bold">Implied</emphasis>. When you create new entities they
                      automatically go under the "Required" list or, depending on the relations that
                      have been created, under the "Implied" list. However, if you want to create an
                      egocentric diagram you can select one of the entities and - through the option
                        <emphasis role="bold">Set as ego (list will be cleared)</emphasis> -
                      transfer it to the "Ego" list. Such entity will go black. [You can also create
                      socialcentric diagrams, in which no particular entity is set as starting point
                      of the diagram.] The option contains the words "list will be cleared", which
                      means that through this command, only one entity can be set as the
                      reference-ego in one diagram; to add more egos, because many diagrams may have
                      been created, you need to use <emphasis role="bold">Add to ego list</emphasis>
                      (see below).</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Add to ego list</emphasis>: this option is similar
                      to the previous one. You can select entities and add them to the "Ego" list in
                      the "Diagram Tree" panel on the left of the page.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Remove from ego list</emphasis>: through this option
                      you can move entities from the "Ego" list back to the "Required" list. </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Keep on diagram</emphasis>: with this option you
                      decide to keep the selected entity/ies on the diagram.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Release from the diagram</emphasis>: with this
                      option you remove the selected entity/ies from the diagram, but in this case
                      it/they remain(s) in the database, unlike with the option "Delete" described
                      above.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Reset Zoom</emphasis>: when selecting this option
                      the zoom of the diagram returns back to its default size.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Reset Layout</emphasis>: it can happen, when you
                      select many entities at a time to put into in the diagram, that they overlap
                      and you cannot see them clearly. By resetting the layout such entities are
                      distanced from each other. </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Save All Data Changes</emphasis>: see point 1.
                      above. </para>
                    <para>
                      <note>
                        <para>You will have to bear in mind the distinction between <emphasis
                            role="underline">permanent</emphasis> and <emphasis role="underline"
                            >temporary</emphasis> entities, i.e. between those which are stored on
                          the diagram when this is saved (the former), and those which, by contrast,
                          go away once the diagram has been saved (the latter). This distinction is
                          marked through the COLOUR of the entities: <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
                              role="underline">black</emphasis> for the permanent ones</emphasis>,
                            <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">grey</emphasis> for the
                            temporary ones</emphasis>. In order to make entitties go black you have
                          to choose the item <emphasis role="bold">Keep on diagram</emphasis>
                          mentioned above. In addition, the same differentiation will appear in the
                            <emphasis role="bold">Diagram Tree</emphasis> tab located on the left of
                          the page (see figure below): all the <emphasis role="bold">permanent
                            entities</emphasis> will be shown under <emphasis role="bold"
                            >Implied</emphasis>, whereas the <emphasis role="bold"
                            >temporary</emphasis> ones will go under <emphasis role="bold"
                            >Required</emphasis>. Newly created entities are, by contrast, black by
                          default.</para>
                      </note>
                    </para>
                    <figure>
                      <title>Standard Diagram</title>
                      <screenshot>
                        <screeninfo/>
                        <mediaobject>
                          <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/StandardDiagram2.png" width="100%"
                              contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"/>
                          </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                      </screenshot>
                    </figure>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Freeform diagram (transient)</emphasis>: when selecting
                this type of diagram, a new page of KinOath will open, with a central, blank panel
                and a smaller panel on the top called <emphasis role="bold">Kin Type
                  Strings</emphasis>. Here too you can create diagrams from scratch but the
                difference from the previous case is that with a freeform diagram you need to enter
                strings in the panel on the top of the page, using precise kin types definitions.
                Immediately below you will find a list of the main ones (which can be also found
                following the path: "Panels" > "Diagram Settings" > "Kin Type Definitions"):</para>
              <para>E = ego; Ef = ego female; Em = ego male; x = undefined</para>
              <para>F or Fa = father; M or Mo = mother; P or Pa = parent</para>
              <para>B or Br = brother; Z or Si = sister; Sb = sibling</para>
              <para>S or So = son; D or Da = daughter; C or Ch = child</para>
              <para>H or Hu = husband; W or Wi = wife; Sp = spouse</para>
              <para>* = first-degree relatives </para>
              <para>Besides the mere kin type definitions, however, you can also add labels to the
                entities, such as names and dates. To do so, you first have to enter a colon after
                the kin type definition and then the label(s). Different labels belonging to the
                same entity need to be separated by a semi-colon. Another colon goes after the last
                label and before the (if any) following kin type definition (see figure below). </para>
              <para>
                <figure>
                  <title>Freeform Diagram</title>
                  <screenshot>
                    <screeninfo/>
                    <mediaobject>
                      <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/FreeformDiagram2.png" width="100%"
                          contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"/>
                      </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                  </screenshot>
                </figure>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Kin Terms Diagram</emphasis>: this type of diagram is
                useful when you want to observe how social relations develop and are named within a
                given language and culture. When you choose this diagram a new page of KinOath
                Kinship Archiver opens, with a central, blank panel, and a smaller panel on the
                right called <emphasis role="bold">Kin Term Group</emphasis>. In the latter, you can
                see a table that has to be filled in order to create the diagram: in the first
                column (<emphasis role="bold">Kin Term</emphasis>) you have to enter, as the name
                itself says, the kin terms that will represent also the labels of the entities in
                the diagram; in the second column (<emphasis role="bold">Referent Kin Type
                  Strings</emphasis>) you have to enter, for each kin term, its corresponding
                definition, i.e. the letters listed in the "Freeform Diagram" paragraph; in the
                fourth column (<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>) you can add, for
                example, an English gloss if the kin terms entered are in another language. In
                addition, you can decide to: a) show the kin terms on the diagram, or hide them, by
                checking or unckecking the option <emphasis role="bold">Show on graph</emphasis>,
                above the table; b) delete some of the kin terms entered in the table by checking
                them and then clicking on <emphasis role="bold">Delete Selected</emphasis>, or c)
                delete the entire kin terms group by simply clicking on <emphasis role="bold">Delete
                  Group</emphasis>, on the left of "Delete Selected". Next to 'Show on graph', there
                is the option <emphasis role="bold">Generate Example Entities</emphasis>; it is
                checked by default and, if you uncheck it, the diagram will not be created. However,
                you can still create a diagram through the kin type strings panel from the panel
                menu. Kin Term diagrams can also be either imported or exported through the options
                  <emphasis role="bold">Import</emphasis>/<emphasis role="bold">Export</emphasis>
                from the Kin Terms panel (see section 2.4 below). There are several sample kin term
                diagrams in the application, reachable via the feature <emphasis role="bold">Open
                  Sample Diagram</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">File</emphasis> menu).</para>
              <para>
                <figure>
                  <title>Kin Terms Diagram</title>
                  <screenshot>
                    <screeninfo/>
                    <mediaobject>
                      <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/KinTermDiagram2.png" width="100%"
                          contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"/>
                      </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                  </screenshot>
                </figure>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Query Diagram</emphasis>: When you choose this diagram a
                new page of KinOath opens, with a central, blank panel, a smaller panel on the left
                containing two, already seen, tabs (<emphasis role="bold">Diagram Tree</emphasis>
                and <emphasis role="bold">Project Tree</emphasis>), and the <emphasis role="bold"
                  >Kin Type Strings</emphasis> panel on the top. This type of diagram allows you to
                search for entities within the entire KinOath Kinship Archiver database. You can
                make a query by using the kin type definitions listed in the "Freeform Diagram"
                paragraph, plus pieces of information such as names, dates. Or, you can directly
                take the entity needed from the "Project Tree" list on the left, and drag it to the
                "Kin Type Strings" panel on the top, preceded by the "E" of "ego". The entities you
                have searched for will appear both in the "Diagram Tree" on the left and in the main
                panel. [If you want to narrow your query open the 'Panels' menu and select the
                'Search Entities' panel]</para>
              <para>
                <figure>
                  <title>Query Diagram </title>
                  <screenshot>
                    <screeninfo/>
                    <mediaobject>
                      <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/queryDiagram.png" contentdepth="100%"
                          scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
                      </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                  </screenshot>
                </figure>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Sample Diagrams</title>
        <para>Apart from the possibility to work on new diagrams, KinOath includes also a list of
          sample diagrams that are useful to observe and to get to know the program and its
          functionalities, and that can be opened through the option "Open Sample Diagram" from the
          File menu. These are: Freeform Diagram Syntax, Query Diagram Syntax, Hawaiian Kin Terms,
          Japanese Kin Terms, Swedish Kin Terms, Named Transient Entities, Matrimonial Ring
          Examples, Charles II of Spain, and Haemophilia in European Royalty. </para>
        <para>
          <note>
            <para>Some hints: press <emphasis role="bold">alt</emphasis> + rotate the mouse wheel to
              zoom the diagram; press <emphasis role="bold">shift</emphasis> + rotate the mouse
              wheel to pan the diagram to the right or to the left; just rotate the mouse wheel to
              scroll the diagram up or down.</para>
          </note>
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Edit menu</title>
      <figure>
        <title>Edit menu</title>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo/>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/EditMenu2.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>This menu contains options related to the modification of a diagram: </para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Select All</emphasis>: by clicking on this option all the
              entities of all the diagrams present in the central panel will be highlighted (i.e.
              they will be sorrounded by a blue, dotted line).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Select Related</emphasis>: if you select one entity and then
              choose this option, all the entities somehow related to the one selected will be
              hightlighted.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Expand Selection</emphasis>: if you select one entity and
              then choose this option, only the entities immediately related to the one selected
              will be highlighted. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Deselect All</emphasis>: this option is for deselecting the
              entities, or the relations between entities, which were previously selected. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recalculate the Diagram</emphasis>: this option allows you
              to partially modify, or totally recreate, a diagram. Once selected you are allowed to
              add: new entities (in the standard diagram), new constraints to new or already
              existing entities (in the freeform and in the query diagrams), new kin terms and kin
              groups (in the kin terms, but also in the freeform, diagram). Alternatively, you can
              simply click on the diagram and the following message will come out: "The diagram
              needs to be recalculated before it can be interacted with. recalculate now?"</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Diagram Options menu</title>
      <figure>
        <title>Diagram Options menu</title>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo/>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/DiagramOptions2.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>This menu contains options related to the layout of a diagram. They only have to be
        checked or unchecked according to the needs. </para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Snap To Grid</emphasis>: this option is checked by default,
              and it allows you to move the entities only in certain ways, as if an imaginary grid
              was there, and the sanguine lines could be placed only on the grid. If unchecked, you
              can move the entities as you want, with no "grid restriction". </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Highlight Selected Relations</emphasis>: if this option is
              checked, when you select one entity, the relations that this one has with other,
              immediately close, entities will be highlighted in blue. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Show Diagram Border</emphasis>: if this option is checked,
              you can see the border of the diagram (a grey line).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Show Sanguin Lines</emphasis>: if this option is unchecked,
              the lines connecting one entity to the other disappear.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Show Labels</emphasis>: if this option is unchecked, the
              labels (names for example) added to the individuals when creating the diagram
              disappear. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Show Kin Type Labels</emphasis>: if this option is
              unchecked, the kin type definitions next to the labels ("EfM" for example)
              disappear.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Show Id Labels</emphasis>: an Id is added when the same kin
              type definition is used for different entities, so that you are able to distinguish
              them; it is represented by a #-sign followed by a number. So, for example, if you have
              two male egos, one will be simply <emphasis role="italic">Em</emphasis>, and the other
                <emphasis role="italic">Em:#1</emphasis>. If this option is unchecked, you are not
              able to see Ids.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Show Date Labels</emphasis>: when you create individuals you
              can also enter, besides name and gender, a date of birth and of death. You may decide
              not to show such dates; if you want them hidden you have to leave this option
              unchecked. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Show Archive Links</emphasis>: this option is valid for the
              diagram type "Archive Data Linker" and for the Gedcom imports that have resources. In
              both cases, the entities that are placed into the diagram will carry a label of the
              type: "archive ref.: 1, 2, etc." (see figure below). Such label disappears if this
              option is unchecked. </para>
            <para>
              <figure>
                <title>Archive Links</title>
                <screenshot>
                  <screeninfo/>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images//archiveLinks.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </figure>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Kin Terms menu</title>
      <figure>
        <title>Kin Terms menu</title>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/KinTermMenu2.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>The whole menu is available only for the Kin Terms Diagram, whereas in the other cases
        only the option <emphasis role="bold">New Kin Term Group</emphasis> can be accessed. This
        menu includes the following options:</para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Show</emphasis>: this option allows you to see the kin terms
              panel on the right of the page. If you uncheck it, the panel disappears and all the
              other menu options are not available anymore. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">New Kin Term Group</emphasis>: this is the only option from
              this menu to be available for all the diagram types. By selecting it, a new tab will
              open in the panel on the right in order to add a new group of kin terms. You can
              choose another colour for this new group by clicking on the bar next to <emphasis
                role="bold">Graph Colour</emphasis> (see figure below). The procedure is the same as
              the one explained above for the Kin Terms Diagram. The new kin terms will appear in
              the diagram next to the ones already present. </para>
            <para>
              <figure>
                <title>New Kin Term Group</title>
                <screenshot>
                  <screeninfo/>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/NewKinTermGroup2.png" width="100%"
                        contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </figure>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Import</emphasis>: instead of creating a new kin term group
              from scratch you may decide to import one already existent from a file directory in
              your computer. To do so, click on <emphasis role="bold">Import</emphasis> and choose
              the file you want to import. The kin terms imported will be added to the ones in the
              table in the right panel and also in the diagram (if a diagram has already been
              created, otherwise they will go and create a new one themselves).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Export</emphasis>: with this option you can save (i.e.
              export) the kin term group just created to a directory outside KinOath. By selecting
              this option a window will open asking you to choose a directory where to place the
              file, and a file name. </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Panels menu</title>
      <figure>
        <title>Panels menu</title>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/PanelsMenu2.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>This menu contains a list of all the panels that can be opened while working on a
        diagram (some of them have already been mentioned when describing the diagram types). You
        can choose which ones you want to open simply by checking them. </para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Active Plugins</emphasis>: this option becomes visible only
              whether, and when, there are, effectively, plugins.  </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Archive Linker</emphasis>: by choosing this option a panel
              will open on the right of the page displaying the entire IMDI corpora. [Note: at the
              moment this panel is not available. See appendix below]</para>
            <para>
              <figure>
                <title>Archive Linker panel</title>
                <screenshot>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/archiveLinker.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                        width="100%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </figure>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Diagram Settings</emphasis>: by choosing this option a panel
              will open on the top of the page with some tabs:</para>
            <para>
              <figure>
                <title>Diagram Settings panel</title>
                <screenshot>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/DiagramSettingsPanel2.png" width="100%"
                        contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </figure>
            </para>
            <para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Entity Profiles</emphasis>: this tab includes a list
                    of profiles which can be added or removed when creating the individuals going
                    into a diagram. They just need to be checked and/or unchecked. See figure
                    above.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Kin Type Definitions</emphasis>: this tab includes a
                    list of the main kin type strings with their corresponding definitions (which
                    have also been described in this manual in section 2.1.1, "Freeform Diagram"
                    paragraph). You can delete elements of the list by checking them and then
                    clicking on the option <emphasis role="bold">Delete Selected </emphasis>on the
                    right of the page. </para>
                  <para>
                    <figure>
                      <title>Kin Type Definitions tab</title>
                      <screenshot>
                        <mediaobject>
                          <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/KinTypeDefinitionsTab.png" width="100%"
                              contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"/>
                          </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                      </screenshot>
                    </figure>
                  </para>
                  <para>Besides, you may want to add new kin types to the list. Bear in mind though,
                    that a new kin type added to a standard diagram behaves differently from a new
                    kin type added to a freeform diagram. Let's make an example: </para>
                  <para>Kin Type String: Q</para>
                  <para>Relation Type: sibling</para>
                  <para>Symbol Type: triangle, circle</para>
                  <para>As far as a standard diagram is concerned, the new kin type represents a
                    filter, which means that when I look up an entity, e.g. Albert_Iof_Monaco, and
                    use the 'Q' kin type, in the central panel I will see the entity searched for,
                    plus all those other individuals (both male and female given the previously set
                    symbol types) carrying a sibling-relation type with it. To put it simply, I will
                    see Albert_Iof_Monaco and his, possibly existing, brother/s and sister/s.</para>
                  <para>By contrast, in the case of a freeform diagram, what the new kin type does
                    is creating new entities from scratch. In other words, if in the Kin Type
                    Strings panel I type, for example, 'EfQ', in the central panel I will see a
                    female ego which is the - so to speak - reference point of my diagram, together
                    with a brother (sibling relation + triangle) and a sister (sibling relation +
                    circle). </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Label Fields</emphasis>: this tab contains some
                    information about the entities created by the user (we are referring to the
                    "Standard Diagram (database driven)" type), i.e. name, date of birth, etc. It
                    may be the case that not all of the fields contained in the table at the bottom
                    of the page, and related to the entity selected, are also shown at the top of
                    the page, i.e. they may not be visible on the diagram. In order to make them
                    appear on the diagram next to the entity, you have to search for them in the
                    drop down menu and click on <emphasis role="bold">Add</emphasis> (see figure
                    below). You can delete the labels by clicking on the small squares on the right
                    of the tab (see red arrow). However, they still remain in the table at the
                    bottom of the page, so if you want to add them back to the panel on the top you
                    just need to take them, one at a time, and drag them to the string of the drop
                    down menu. <figure>
                      <title>Label Fields tab</title>
                      <screenshot>
                        <mediaobject>
                          <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/LabelFieldsTab2.png" width="100%"
                              contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"/>
                          </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                      </screenshot>
                    </figure></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Relation Type Definitions</emphasis>: through this tab
                    you can add details to the relations between the entities. It has some sub-tabs:
                      <emphasis role="bold">Custom Name</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Data
                      Category</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Relation Type</emphasis> (which, in
                    turn, lets you choose among <emphasis role="italic">sibling</emphasis>,
                      <emphasis role="italic">ancestor (descendant)</emphasis>, <emphasis
                      role="italic">descendant (ancestor)</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic"
                      >union</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">kinterm</emphasis>, <emphasis
                      role="italic">other</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">undirected</emphasis>,
                      <emphasis role="italic">directedin (directedout)</emphasis>, <emphasis
                      role="italic">directedout (directedin)</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic"
                      >&lt;any></emphasis>); <emphasis role="bold">Line Colour</emphasis>; <emphasis
                      role="bold">Line Width</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Line/Dash</emphasis>,
                      <emphasis role="bold">Curve Line Orientation</emphasis>. Look at the picture
                    below to see how they work. </para>
                  <para>
                    <figure>
                      <title>Relation Type Definition Tab</title>
                      <screenshot>
                        <screeninfo/>
                        <mediaobject>
                          <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/RelationTypeDefinitionTab.png"
                              contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
                          </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                      </screenshot>
                    </figure>
                    <note>
                      <para>As far as sibling lines are concerned (Relation Type > sibling), these
                        won't be rendered if they have common parents.</para>
                    </note>
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Symbol Fields</emphasis>: according to the features
                    that are attributed to the entities, these get different shapes, for example a
                    female ego is a circle, whereas a male ego is a triangle. Such shapes, however,
                    can be modified by choosing among the possibilities included in the drop down
                    lists on the right of the panel. </para>
                  <para>
                    <figure>
                      <title>Symbol Fields tab</title>
                      <screenshot>
                        <screeninfo/>
                        <mediaobject>
                          <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/SymbolFieldsTab.png" width="100%"
                              contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"/>
                          </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                      </screenshot>
                    </figure>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <note>
                      <para>Not all of the options just explained are available for all the diagram
                        types. They vary according the diagram type and, therefore, according to the
                        diagram purposes.</para>
                    </note>
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Diagram Tree</emphasis>: this panel opens up on the left of
              the page. It displays three possible lists: <emphasis role="bold">Ego</emphasis>,
                <emphasis role="bold">Required</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Implied</emphasis>. </para>
            <para>When you create new individuals, they automatically go under the "Required" list.
              If you want an egocentric diagram, you have to add an ego (or several egos if you want
              to create several diagrams), to the "Ego" list (right click on the entity > Set as Ego
              (list will be cleared)). The ego added to the list goes black and represents the
              reference point of your diagram. </para>
            <para>
              <figure>
                <title>Diagram Tree Panel</title>
                <screenshot>
                  <screeninfo/>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/DiagramTreeTab3.png" contentdepth="100%"
                        scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </figure>
            </para>
            <para>By comparison, when you search for an already existing entity, you will see the
              ego of your diagram under the Ego list and, on the other hand, under the "Implied"
              list, there will be all those entities that are automatically linked to the one
              selected. See figure below. </para>
            <para>
              <figure>
                <title>Diagram Tree panel 2</title>
                <screenshot>
                  <screeninfo/>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/DiagramTreeTab2.png" contentdepth="100%"
                        scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </figure>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Kin Terms</emphasis>: this panel opens up automatically when
              working on a "Kin Terms" diagram (see section 2.4).</para>
            <para>
              <figure>
                <title>Kin Terms panel</title>
                <screenshot>
                  <screeninfo/>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/kinTermsPanel.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                        width="100%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </figure>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Kin Type Strings</emphasis>: this panel opens up
              automatically in case of a freeform or a query diagram. In it you type the strings
              necessary to create new individuals (freeform diagram) or to look for them (query
              diagram). (see section 2.1.1 above, Freeform Diagram paragraph)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Search Entities</emphasis>: this option is available for the
              standard and the query diagram, which are both database driven. Indeed, its function
              is to search for specific entities in the database. To do so, you have to type the
              name of the entity in the white string included in this tab and press "Enter", or
              click on <emphasis role="bold">Search</emphasis>. You can also search for related
              entities by checking the option <emphasis role="bold">Expand Selection by Kin Type
                String</emphasis> and by entering a kin type definition of the type seen before.
              (see figure below)</para>
            <para>
              <figure>
                <title>Search Entities</title>
                <screenshot>
                  <screeninfo/>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images//SearchEntitiesTab.png" contentdepth="100%"
                        scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </figure>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Plugins menu</title>
      <para>This menu simply shows you which plugins are active on the application in that ongoing
        session. If no plugins are present, then you will only see: &lt;no plugins found>. This
        structure provides the application with even more flexibility, and makes it possible for
        third parties to develop new features.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Window menu</title>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Window menu</title>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo/>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/WindowMenu2.png" contentdepth="100%" width="100%"
                  scalefit="1"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>The options of this menu vary according to how many windows of KinOath have been opened.
        Indeed, it simply consists of a list of the options that have been selected and opened:
        sample diagrams, new diagrams, etc. Each window has its corresponding menu option checked. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Help menu</title>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Help menu</title>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo/>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/HelpMenu2.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                  width="100%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>This menu includes some additional information about the program:</para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">About</emphasis>: by selecting this option a dialog window
              will open, briefly describing the program. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Internal Help</emphasis>: it opens the instructions manual
              onto a new page of the application.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">KinOath Website</emphasis>: it redirects you to the web page
              of the application (<ulink url="http://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/kinoath"
                >http://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/kinoath</ulink>).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">KinOath Online Manual</emphasis>: it links you to the online
              version of the manual, located on the TLA webpage (<ulink
                url="http://www.mpi.nl/corpus/html/kinoath/index.html"
                >http://www.mpi.nl/corpus/html/kinoath/index.html</ulink>)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">KinOath Forum (Website)</emphasis>: by selecting this option
              you will be redirected to the following page: <ulink
                url="http://tla.mpi.nl/forums/software/kinoath"
                >http://tla.mpi.nl/forums/software/kinoath</ulink>, a discussion board page where
              you can start discussions about topics relevant to KinOath Kinship Archiver. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">View Error Log</emphasis>: by selecting this option a page
              in NotePad will open, containing the possible errors encountered while using the
              program. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Reindex all files</emphasis>: this option may turn out
              useful when, for example, you are working with some entity files on one particular
              version of the application, but you then realize that you need a different version,
              and you have to transfer all the entity files from one to the other. To put it in
              other words, this feature enables you to synchronize the entity files on the
              application with the ones present on the disk. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Check for Updates</emphasis>: this option allows you to
              search for more recent versions of KinOath Kinship Archiver.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>How to...?</title>
    <para>This chapter is aimed at summarizing the main content of the manual in a practical way. To
      put it differently, here you will find straightforward instructions that will help you become
      a bit more familiar with the application. </para>
    <section>
      <title>...add entities via right click menu</title>
      <para>There exist two possible ways of adding new entities to your - standard type - diagram.
        The first one is the following: </para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>[If you do not already have a project-based diagram open (see section 2.1 above -
              option 'Open Diagram')] From the <emphasis role="bold">File</emphasis> menu select
                <emphasis role="bold">New Diagram of Type</emphasis> and then <emphasis role="bold"
                >Standard Diagram (database driven)</emphasis>;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Point the mouse inside the main, white panel and right click. Select the first
              item of the menu: <emphasis role="bold">Add</emphasis>, and then one of the five items
              that come up: <emphasis role="bold">Individual</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold"
                >Chromosome_Example</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Clan_Example</emphasis>,
                <emphasis role="bold">KinTerm</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold"
                >Social_Event</emphasis>. Regardless of which one you choose, an entity represented
              by a small square will appear in the main panel. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select the just mentioned item; a table at the bottom of the page will open with
              several fields to fill in. The fields vary for the different entity profiles mentioned
              in the previous point. Once you have entered the required information click again on
              the entity, it will change accordingly (e.g. depending on its gender the square will
              turn into a circle or a triangle).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>...add/remove relations</title>
      <para>After creating a certain amount of entities you may want to create also relations
        between them. To do so:</para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select the two, or more, entities you need (SHIFT key being hold down); right
              click; choose the menu item <emphasis role="bold">Add relation</emphasis>, and then
              select the type of relation you want. The entities will be linked accordingly.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>As for the relation types <emphasis role="bold">ancestor</emphasis> and <emphasis
                role="bold">descendant</emphasis>, remember that: if you select first the ancestor,
              and then the descendant, you have to choose a descendant relation type. By comparison,
              if you do it the other way round, i.e. first descendant and then ancestor, you have to
              choose an ancestor relation type. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>If you decide to remove some of the relations just created, select again how many
              entities you need (SHIFT key being hold down) and right click; choose the menu item
                <emphasis role="bold">Remove Relations</emphasis> and then <emphasis role="bold"
                >Remove relations between selected</emphasis>. The line linking the entities will go
              away.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>...release VS delete entities</title>
      <para>There are two options through which you can remove entities from your diagram:</para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Delete</emphasis>: the delete option will remove an entity
              from all the diagrams, and also from the database. Once you select it (select the
              entity/ies you want to remove and right click) a message will pop up telling you that
              a number of entities will be deleted from the database.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Release from diagram</emphasis>: this option (select the
              needed entity/ies > right click) will simply remove an entity from the diagram, but
              unlike 'delete' it will <emphasis role="underline">not</emphasis> remove it from the
              database. </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>...add entities via search tab</title>
      <para>The second way to add entities to your diagram is through the Search Entities
        tab:</para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Follow the same steps explained in section 3.1, i.e. [If you do not already have a
              project-based diagram open (see section 2.1 above - option 'Open Diagram')] File menu
              > New Diagram of Type > Standard diagram (database driven). </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>On the left of the page select the tab <emphasis role="bold">Search
                Entities</emphasis>. In the white field under <emphasis role="bold">Search Entity
                Names</emphasis> type the name of an entity that you know is present in the
              database; then click <emphasis role="bold">Search</emphasis>. In the white column
              under 'Search' you will see a list of all the entities (partially) matching your
              query. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The option <emphasis role="bold">Graph selection</emphasis> (below the 'Search
              Entity Names' white field) is checked by default; this means that when you select an
              entity from the list given to you after the query is made, this will automatically
              appear in the main panel. If you uncheck this option, you will have to manually drag
              the selected entity to the main panel. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Another option that may turn useful is <emphasis role="bold">Expand selection by
                kin type string</emphasis> (below 'Graph selection'). If you check it, and then
              enter some kin types in the white field below it, you will see the previously selected
              entity changing accordingly. E.g. (after having imported the sample data 'European
              Royalty') type 'Albert' and then click 'Search'. Select one of the entities that
              appear in the list: it will appear also in the main panel. Then check the field
              'Expand selection...' and type '*'. All (if any) first-degree relatives related to the
              entity selected will appear on the diagram as well. </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>...create a freeform diagram</title>
      <para>The instructions given above applied to the diagram type standard - database driven.
        This section, by comparison, is about another diagram type: the freeform diagram. Here is
        how it works:</para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>[If you do not already have a project-based diagram open (see section 2.1 above -
              option 'Open Diagram')] From the File menu select New Diagram of Type and then
                <emphasis role="bold">Freeform Diagram (transient)</emphasis>. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>In the tab on top of the page - <emphasis role="bold">Kin Type Strings</emphasis>
              - type the strings with which you want to create your diagram. A list of the main kin
              types is given in section 2.1.1 above. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>To the kin types you can attach some labels, namely names, dates, etc. To do so,
              enter a colon after the kin type, then separate each of the label with a semi-colon,
              and finally enter another colon between the last label and the next kin type. The
              labels have to be entered with a precise order: Id [mind that the Id is normally used
              when you have two entities with the same kin type definition], name, date of birth -
              date of death. E.g. Ef:Jane;1950-2010:M:Carla;1925-2000:.....</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>...create a query diagram</title>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>[If you do not already have a project-based diagram open (see section 2.1 above -
              option 'Open Diagram')] From the File menu, select New Diagram of Type and then
                <emphasis role="bold">Query Diagram</emphasis>. As the name says, this diagram is
              mainly used when you want to search for entities within the ones present in the
              database.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>What you can do here is either type something for yourself, or directly use the
              entities in the tab <emphasis role="bold">Project Tree</emphasis> on the left of the
              page.</para>
            <para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>In the first case, you can type something like 'x[Albert_I]' in the tab 'Kin
                    Type Strings' on top of the page: in the main panel you will see all the
                    entities named Albert_I and/or containing Albert_I in their names. Besides, you
                    can add futher kin types like 'x[Albert_I]*', in which case you will see all the
                    possibly existing first-degree relatives of all the entities present in the main
                    panel.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>In the second case, by comparison, you can select an entity in particular
                    from the 'Project Tree' tab and drag it to the Kin Type Strings tab on top of
                    the page, preceded either by E or x, which stand for any, unspecified entity
                    [note that if you want to narrow the field of search you can always open the
                    'Search Entities' tab via 'Panels' menu]. E.g.
                    x[Entity.Identifier=7bd7bff7-ff5e-4424-a9c9-d1283e0df145]; in the main panel you
                    will see only that entity in particular. As in the previous case, you can also
                    add further kin types, and the diagram in the main panel will change
                    accordingly. </para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>...create a kin terms diagram</title>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>[If you do not already have a project-based diagram open (see section 2.1 above -
              option 'Open Diagram')] From the File menu, select New Diagram of Type and <emphasis
                role="bold">Kin Terms Diagram</emphasis>. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>In the tab on the right of the page, fill in the table (for the moment you can
              skip <emphasis role="bold">Propositus Kin Type Strings</emphasis>). The header
                <emphasis role="bold">Kin Term</emphasis> is quite straightforward: enter the kin
              terms; under the header <emphasis role="bold">Referent Kin Type Strings</emphasis>
              enter the kin types corresponding to the kin terms previously written; under <emphasis
                role="bold">Description</emphasis> you can put, for example, the English gloss of
              the kin terms (if these are in a different language). </para>
            <para>E.g.: Italian kin terms</para>
            <para>Kin Term - padre; Referent Kin Type Strings - EF; Description: father</para>
            <para>K.T. - madre; R.K.T.S. - EM; D. - mother</para>
            <para>K.T. - fratello; R.K.T.S. - EB; D. - brother</para>
            <para>K.T. - sorella; R.K.T.S. - EZ; D. - sister</para>
            <para>etc. The diagram will grow as you add kin terms.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>If you want to create a new kin term group [take Japanese Kin Terms sample diagram
              as reference: File > Open Sample Diagram > Japanese Kin Terms] go to <emphasis
                role="bold">Kin Terms</emphasis> menu on top of the page and select <emphasis
                role="bold">New Kin Term Group</emphasis>. A second tab will open on the right of
              the page. It is of the same type as the one you already used and the table in it needs
              to be filled in the same way (choose a different color so that the two kin term groups
              can be easily distinguished). </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Two functions that you may use while working on a kin terms diagram are: a)
              importing previously created and saved kin terms; b) exporting the ones you have just
              created. As for the former, go to Kin Terms menu and select <emphasis role="bold"
                >Import</emphasis>. A window will open asking you to choose a file. Choose the one
              you need and select <emphasis role="bold">Open</emphasis>. The kin terms will appear
              both in the table on the right of the page and in the main panel in the form of
              diagram. Besides, another window popping up will tell you how many kin terms have been
              imported. As for exporting, select the option <emphasis role="bold">Export</emphasis>
              from the Kin Terms menu. A window will open asking you to choose a directory where to
              export the kin terms and a file name; then select <emphasis role="bold"
                >Save</emphasis>. The kin terms will be exported to the chosen directory. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Finally, there are two more options you can use: 1) <emphasis role="bold">Show on
                graph</emphasis>. It is checked by default, which implies that you are able to see
              the actual kin terms. If you unckeck it, the kin terms will be removed from the
              diagram but kept in the table. 2) <emphasis role="bold">Generate Example
                Entities</emphasis>. It is checked by default as well, and it allows you to see the
              diagram developing and growing as you enter new kin terms. If you uncheck it, the
              whole diagram will go away (but the kin terms, like in the previous case, are kept in
              the table). </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <appendix>
    <title>Features not available in KinOath 1.2 </title>
    <para>
      <note>
        <para>As you may have noticed, KinOath 1.2 presents some hidden options. These features are
          not implemented at the moment, but will be available in the next releases of the
          application. However, they are already available in the current testing version.</para>
      </note>
    </para>
    <para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Export as JPEG/PNG/TIFF</emphasis> (File menu) [Note: PDF
            format works!]. These feature fails on the webstart, but it works if KinOath is
            installed;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Add Polyline</emphasis> (Standard Diagram > right click menu >
            Add Geometry);</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Propositus Kin Type Strings</emphasis> (File menu > New
            Diagram of Type > Kin Terms Diagram > table on the right of the page > third
            column);</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Delete Group</emphasis> ((File menu > New Diagram of Type >
            Kin Terms Diagram > panel on the right of the page);</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Archive Data Linker</emphasis> diagram (File menu > New
            Diagram of Type > Archive Data Linker);</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Archive Linker</emphasis> menu (top of the page).</para>
          <para/>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <para>For further information on KinOath Kinship Archiver, please refer to the following
      links:</para>
    <para>
      <ulink url="http://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/kinoath/requests/"
        >http://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/kinoath/requests/</ulink>; on this page you will find a
      list of already known issues about KinOath 1.2, and of some feature requests which will be
      possibly implemented either in KinOath 1.3 - 1.4 or in other kiship studies related
      contexts.</para>
    <para><ulink url="http://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/kinoath/changes/"
        >http://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/kinoath/changes/</ulink>; on this page, by contrast, you
      can see a list showing which changes have been made to which version of the application. </para>
  </appendix>
</book>
